Guide to the William Appleton Aiken Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Appleton Aiken papers
1891-1971
MS 1093
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
(21 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, research materials, and autograph letters relating to the literary work of William Appleton Aiken on the life of Daniel Fitch, second Earl of Nottingham. Also included are Aiken's personal papers including his diaries as an army intelligence officer in the Middle East during World War II and an exhibition scrapbook prepared by the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information.
Aiken, William Appleton, 1907-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William A. Aiken, 1959; acquired from Seaport Autographs, 1993 and Noushin Books & Co., 2014.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Appleton Aiken consist of manuscripts, transcripts and photostatic copies of papers in British and American repositories, notes, correspondence, photographs, and other papers relating to Daniel Finch, second Earl of Nottingham, and his period. The bulk of the collection is research materials for Aiken's Yale doctoral thesis, The Conduct of the Rt. Hon. Daniel Earl of Nottingham, By Himself (1939; published in 1941 under the title, The Conduct of the Earl of Nottingham, and for other writings on related topics. The research materials have been left in Aiken's order.
Aiken's manuscripts are largely critical editions of writings by Nottingham and his contemporaries, although several short articles are also included. His correspondence consists of letters from Jasmine Finch about her family's history, from Aiken's research assistant, A. May Osler, and from historians and scholars sending congratulations on the publication of his book. Included are Stuart W. Jackson, Wallace Notestein, Paul D. Moody, and George M. Trevelyan.
Also in the collection, although unrelated to the other materials, are two autograph letters of 1897, one from Cosima Wagner and the other from Hedwig Humperdinck, both addressed to Charles Joseph Dyer.
Also included are Aiken's personal papers including his diaries as an army intelligence officer in the Middle East during World War II and an exhibition scrapbook prepared by the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information.
Biographical / Historical
WILLIAM APPLETON AIKEN. Professor of English and European history, Lehigh University; residence, 1324 Prospect Avenue, Bethlehem, Pa. "Appy", who joined the Lehigh faculty as assistant professor of English history in 1941, was appointed associate professor of English and European history in February, 1946, and to a full professorship in January, 1949. He received an M.Litt. degree at Cambridge University in 1932 and a Ph.D. at Yale in 1939-both in English history-and was an instructor in history at McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, from 1938 to 1940. He is a member of the social studies committee of the College Entrance Board Examinations of the Educational Testing Service, Princeton, N.J., and secretary to the National Council of the American Friends of the Middle East. He belongs to the American Historical Association, the American Academy of Social and Political Science, the Archeological Institute of America, the Middle East Institute, and the Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities. Appy edited The Conduct of the Earl of Nottingham (Yale University Press, 1941), arranged and edited The Poems of Catullus (Dutton, 1950), and is the author of an article on the Middle East in This Week Magazine in 1951 and of two articles on Cairo, published in Egypt in 1952.
From June, 1942, to February, 1946, he served in the Psychological Warfare Branch (first lieutenant to major)-in Washington most of the time, although he spent four months abroad (London and Cairo). Appy, who received a citation for distinguished service-or whatever you call that white and green ribbon"-has continued in the Reserve and in the past few years has attended the O.R.C. School. Command and General Staff Section, in Allentown, Pa.
Married on June 2, 1938, in New York City to Phyllis Almy Gallatin, he has three children: Timothy Buckingham, born June 23, 1940, in Mt. Kisco, N.Y., Penelope Gallatin on April 24, 1942, in Bethlehem, and David MacGregor on October 11, 1949, in New York.
(History of the Class of 1929, Yale college, 25 Year Record, pages 30-31)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Military intelligence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence; Europe; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 18th century; Great Britain; Middle East; Autographs (manuscripts); Educators; Historians; Aiken, William Appleton, 1907-1957; Jackson, Stuart W. (Stuart Wells), 1875-; Moody, Paul D. (Paul Dwight), 1879-1947; Notestein, Wallace, 1878-1969; Nottingham, Daniel Finch, Earl of, 1647-1730; Osler, A. May; Trevelyan, George Macaulay, 1876-1962; Lehigh University -- Faculty
- Inventory, 1897, 1934-1949, undated; 4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1942, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Short writings
    - Adapted text of first act of Sedney's "Bellamira", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Daniel Finch and the Admiralty Commission, 1679-1684", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Many Worlds of Daniel Finch", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Peer's Passage Across France: Glimpses of the Grand Tour in the Year 1772", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Whig Oligarchs and American Colonies", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Drafts for an article on the opening of the Convention Parliament, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes for a lecture on Nottingham, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Critical editions of historical papers
    - "Characters of Four Noblemen in the Reign of William III", undated (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - "Memoirs in the Reigns of King Charles II, King James II, King William III and Queen Mary", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Observations and Opinions of a Noble Lord in the Reign of King Charles II", undated (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
    - "Chp. II. Reflections Upon the Late Revolution, 1688", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Chp. V. Discourse on the Peace, 1712 (The Madness of Party)", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Part II: A Narrative of Events Naval and Political, 1689-1694", undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Research materials
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 3, Folder 21-58)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 4, Folder 59-93)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 5, Folder 94-119)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 6, Folder 120-143)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 7, Folder 144-169)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 8, Folder 170-204)
    - Transcripts, notes, and other materials, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 9, Folder 205-231)
    - Inventories of original documents used, 1934-1941, undated (Box 9, Folder 232-240)
    - "Chronological Outline", undated (Box 9, Folder 241)
    - "Outline: Eng. Const. Hist.", undated (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Photographs of Mss for thesis, [1939] (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - Photographs and miscellaneous items re: Conduct of the Earl of Nottingham, 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 244)
  - Autograph letters
    - Humperdinek, Hedwig (Mrs. Engelbert), 1897 December 31 (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - Wagner, Cosima (Mrs. Richard), 1897 April 11 (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - Card file, [ca. 1934-1941] (Box 10–11)
- Additional Material, 1891, 1919-1971, undated; Accession 1993-M-070; 4 linear feet (8 boxes, 1 folio)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1994 Oct
  Received from: Acquired from Seaport Autographs, 1993 Apr 30
  - Family correspondence
    - Clare College, England: family correspondence, printed material, [1930 Oct?]-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Family correspondence (removed from binder), 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Letters from McMaster University, Ontario, 1938 October-1939 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Family correspondence, 1940-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Letters to the Family": vol. III, 1948 April (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Letters to the Family", 1948 May-September (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Aiken, W.A. to Phyllis Aiken (Gallatin), 1935-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "The Bounds of Convention": autobiographical letter to children, 1945 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Aiken, Anna (aunt), (Mrs. Alfred Aiken), 1947 December 27-1957 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - Aiken, Phyllis (Mrs. William A. Aiken), 1953-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    - Aiken, Timothy (son), 1954-1955, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General correspondence/subject files
    - A-F (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bach Choir and Festival, (Bethlehem, PA), 1949, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Biographical materials, 1957-1958, 1969,undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Business/legal materials, 1939, 1957, 1967, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Clare College, England: applications, 1928-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Finances, 1929-1939, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Fulbright and Guggenheim awards, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - G-L (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Genealogy, 1891, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Groton School, Massachusetts; St. Paul's School, New Hampshire: applications, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Joint Chiefs of Staff consultant position, 1946 May 22-1947 1947 May 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Labaree, Leonard W.: correspondence pertaining to the Yale University Press publication of W. A. Aiken's The Conduct of the Earl of Nottingham, 1940-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - M-R (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - McClenaghan, Worsfold, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "New Strategy in the Middle East," by W. A. Aiken, NY Herald Tribune (with accompanying correspondence), 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "The New Statesman and Nation" and cover letter, 1951 October 20, 27, November 3, 20 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Notestein, Wallace, 1938-1941, 1947, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - S-T (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - U-Z (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - History lecture notecards, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Lecture notes, 1938, 1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 39-44)
  - Writings of W. A. Aiken (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Poetry selections, 1925, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "A Great Pessimist: A Great Poet: A Discussion of Matthew Arnold and his Poetry", undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Book review of The Ugly Duchess, by Feuchtwanger, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "The Biographies of Alexander Hamilton", undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - The Admirality in Conflict and Commission, 1679-1684, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - The Conduct of the Rt. Hon. Daniel Earl of Nottingham by Himself: PhD dissertation, annotated typescript, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - The Conduct of the Rt. Hon. Daniel Earl of Nottingham by Himself: PhD dissertation typescript, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - The Conduct of the Earl of Nottingham, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - "Man so Various, or, the Conscience of Others", 1957 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - The Administration of Daniel Finch, Second Earl of Nottingham, as Secretary of State under Queen Anne, 1702-1704, undated (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Writings of others
    - "Sun Rays and Moon Beams," by Mary Gallatin Hoppin, undated (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - "Web of Days": selections by Barbara Leslie Jordan, undated (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Detailed description of the World War II diaries of W. A. Aiken, prepared by Norman F. Boas, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Lecture notes for intelligence training, 1942 February-August (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Wartime diary, 1943 January 1-March 9 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - "Notes on a Diary" (7 diaries), 1943 March 10-May 15 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - "Journal of a Trip to the Near and Middle East between Nov [Dec] 1943 and Feb 1944" (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Handwritten notes, 1943 December 21-January 13, 1944 January 13-January 21 (Box 8, Folder 57-58)
    - "Part I: Journey to London to Middle East": typescript of handwritten notes, 1943 November 4-1944 January 17 (Box 8, Folder 59-61)
    - "Part II: Journey to Jerusalem": typescript of handwritten notes, 1944 January 18-23 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - "Part III: Contacts in Cairo": typescript of handwritten notes, 1944 January 24-February 13 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - "Part IV: London Revisited" (this part is missing) (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Memorabilia/miscellany, 1922, 1938-1954, 1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Diaries, 1924, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 65-66)
  - Aiken, Phyllis (Gallatin): address book, photograph case, undated (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Photographs, 1900s-(1950s-1960s), undated (Box 9, Folder 68-69)
  - Negatives, unidentified, Undated (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - FOLIO
    - Oil painting of carnations, signed "Aiken", undated (Box 10)
- Additional Material, 1944-1945; Accession 2014-M-065; 1; (1 box)
  - Exhibition scrapbook prepared by the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information for presentation to the Civil Affairs Division of the War Department, 1944-1945 (Box 1)